Guide to the Performing arts manuscripts collection, circa 1475-1984
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Performing arts manuscripts collection
circa 1475-1984
C0215
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
4.0 linear feet (4 boxes)
Collection consists of photographic prints, lithographs, drawings, and written manuscripts pertaining to significant musicians, composers, dancers, and their works.
Gerber, Steven K.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection materials were purchased from a variety of rare book and manuscript dealers from 2009 through the present.
Historical Information
The Performing arts manuscripts collection consists of items selected by Steven Gerber, the Music, Theater, and Philosophy Librarian at George Mason University (GMU). In addition to his librarian duties, Gerber teaches courses on music research and bibliography at GMU. He developed this collection to serve as a resource for his courses and to provide research access for GMU performing arts faculty and students.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of photographic prints, lithographs, and drawings of significant musicians, composers, and dancers. The photographs depict portraits and images of professional performing artists at work. The drawings and lithographs are primarily portraits of notable performing arts professionals, or feature subject matter related to the performing arts, including costume design and scenes from various stage sets and performances. The collection also contains several manuscripts, including a folio of musical instruments, a stage guide and score for the musical "My Maryland," and hand-written sheet music.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series. Each series is arranged chronologically by order of acquisition.
Series 1: Graphic Materials, 1610-1940 (Boxes 1-4)
Series 2: Manuscripts, circa 1475-1929 (Boxes 1, 3)
Series 3: Photographs, 1900-1984 (Boxes 1-3)
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center holds published materials related to music and the performing arts which can be found through the George Mason University library catalog. Special Collections Research Center also holds many other
Index Terms
Persons:
Ailey, Alvin -- Photographs; Arne, Thomas Augustine, 1710-1778 -- Pictorial works; Balanchine, George -- Photographs; Basili, Francesco, 1767-1850; Bernstein, Leonard, 1918-1990 -- Photographs; Bolm, Adolf, 1884-1951 -- Photographs; Cage, John -- Photographs; Cherubini, Luigi, 1760-1842 -- Pictorial works; Danilova, Alexandra, 1907-1997; Dello Joio, Norman, 1913-2008 -- Photographs; Didelot, Rose Colinette -- Pictorial works; Duncan, Isadora, 1877-1927 -- Photographs; Eglevsky, Andre -- Photographs; Fuller, Loie, 1862-1928 -- Photographs; Germania Musical Society. -- Pictorial works; Graham, Martha -- Photographs; Griffith, Robert E. -- Photographs; Kabalevsky, Dmitry Borisovich, 1904-1987 -- Photographs; Kodaly, Zoltan, 1882-1967 -- Photographs; Laurents, Arthur -- Photographs; Lifar, Serge, 1905-1986 -- Photographs; Mascagni, Pietro, 1863-1945; Massenet, Jules, 1842-1912; Mitchell, Arthur, 1934- -- Photographs; Mumma, Gordon, 1935- -- Photographs; Novikoff, Laurent -- Photographs; Partch, Harry, 1901-1974 -- Photographs; Pavlova, Anna, 1881-1931 -- Pictorial works; Prince, Harold, 1928- -- Photographs; Ram Gopal, 1917- -- Photographs; Robbins, Jerome -- Photographs; Romberg, Sigmund, 1887-1951; Rossini, Gioachino, 1792-1868; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967 -- Photographs; Sondheim, Stephen -- Photographs; Tudor, David, 1926-1996 -- Photographs; Viardot-Garcia, Pauline, 1821-1910
Corporate Names:
Ballet Russe de Monte-Carlo.; Ballets russes.
Subjects:
Ballet--Pictorial works.; Costume design.; Dance; Hitler Youth--Photographs.; Minstrel shows; Music.; No; Opera.; Performing arts.; Sheet music.; Stage guides; Theater.; Tom and Jerry (Television program)
Document Types:
Lithographs.; Etchings.; Photographic prints.
Contents List
- Series 1: Graphic Materials, 1610-1940 (Boxes 1-4)
  - Engraving by Israel Silvestre of a scene from the opera "La Princesse d'Elide" by Moliere and Lully, circa 1673 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Acquisition date - October 2009
  - Thomas Arne painted by R. Dunkarton and engraved by W. Humphrey, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Acquisition date - December 2009
  - Original set design by David de Boschi for an unidentified ballet, circa 1830-1840 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Acquisition date - February 2010
  - Four illustrations by Ernst Oppler of Anna Pavlova in "The Dying Swan", 1914-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Acquisition date - September 2010
  - Engraving by Mattias Kusel of a scene from the opera "Il Pomo d'Oro" by Antonio Cesti, circa 1666 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Acquisition date - October 2011
  - "Menuet de la Cour" drawing attributed to Le Couteur, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Caricature drawing by Zara Simeowi of Nazi officers and onlookers singing around a piano, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Acquisition date - March 2012
  - Print by Conde and Reynolds of Rose Didelot in the Character of Calypso, circa 1791 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Osculetor me osculo oris sui; Canticum, canticorum" engraved by Claes Jansz Visscher, 1610 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Call number NE671.16.V58 1610; Acquisition date - September 2013
  - Costumes for ten characters from the opera "Oberon", circa 1800s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Acquisition date - October 2016
  - Engraving by William Blake of a scene from the opera "The Beggar's Opera" by J. C. Pepusch, circa 1790-1827 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Acquisition date - February 2017
  - Engraving by Mattias Kusel of a scene from the opera "Il Pomo d'Oro" by Antonio Cesti, circa 1666 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Caricature drawings by Thomas Nast of the Grand Masquerade Ball given at the Academy of Music, circa 1866 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lithograph by Jean-Gabriel Scheffer from the series "Ce Qu'on Dit et Ce Qu'on Pense" depicting Gioachino Rossini speaking to a young man, circa 1830 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Acquisition date - December 2017
  - Etching by Jean Jacques de Boissieu of dancers and musicians in a country setting, 1773 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lithographed portrait by L. Loire of singer Pauline Viardot (Garcia), circa 1839 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Acquisition date - January 2016
  - Six hand-colored lithographs of character costume designs for the opera "Cavalleria Rusticana", circa 1890 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Acquisition date - May 2016
  - Four lithographs by E. Buval of a scene and three costumed characters from the opera "La Navarraise", circa 1894 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lithographic portrait by Charles Bour of Italian composer Luigi Cherubini, circa 1800s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Acquisition date - June 2012
  - Seven watercolor drawings of character costume designs for a production of the opera "Aida", circa 1800s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Acquisition date - September 2016
  - Watercolor costume design for a production of the opera "Aida", circa 1800s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Four original images from the 1952 Tom and Jerry short "Johann Mouse", circa 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Acquisition date - September 2017
  - Plan for a fireworks display for King George II to be accompanied by music composed by George Frideric Handel, circa 1749 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Acquisition date - March 2018
  - Japanese hand-painted scroll of Noh theater masks, circa 1880s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Call number PN2924.5.N6 H36 1880z; Acquisition date - March 2018
- Series 2: Manuscripts, circa 1475-1929 (Boxes 1, 3)
  - "Musical instruments" folio by Denis Diderot, circa 1751-1772 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript leaf from a choir book in Latin, circa 1500 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Call number Oversize M2147 XV .M3; Acquisition date - February 2017
  - Manuscript leaf from a choir book in Latin, circa 1475-1525 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Call number Oversize M2147 XVI .M4; Acquisition date - February 2017
  - "Missa Choralis Unisona" musical manuscript, circa 1800s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Call number M2013.5 .M58 1700z; Acquisition date - September 2017
  - "Justus ut palma a 3 Canto e Alto e Basso" by Francesco Basili, circa 1800-1825 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Call number M2019.5.B38 J88 1800z; Acquisition date - September 2016
  - "My Maryland" musical romance in three acts, circa 1929 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Call number Folio M1503.R75 M9 1929; Acquisition date - July 2017
  - Score for "My Maryland" musical, circa 1929 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Call number Folio M1503.R75 M9 1929 score; Acquisition date - July 2017
- Series 3: Photographs, 1900-1984 (Boxes 1-3)
  - Dancer and choreographer Jerome Robbins and ballerinas rehearsing "Circus Polka", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Choreographer George Balanchine rehearsing two dancers in "Adagio Lamentoso", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photograph by Blake Studios of Russian dancer Laurent Novikoff of Ballets Russes, circa 1900s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photograph of dancer and choreographer Loie Fuller with printed program for a performance by her troupe, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poet and folklorist Carl Sandburg playing guitar, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Two photographs of Russian dancer Theodore Kosloff and dance ensemble from MGM film "Madame Satan", 1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Acquisition date - March 2015
  - Photograph by Van Vechten of dancer and choreographer Alvin Ailey, March 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photograph by Maurice Goldberg of the Isadora Duncan Dancers, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photograph by Harcourt of Russian dancer Serge Lifar of Ballets Russes, circa 1900s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photograph and autograph of Indian dancer and choreographer Ram Gopal in "Golden Eagle" costume, circa 1900s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Two photographs by Martha Swope of choreographer Jerome Robbins rehearsing dancers from the New York City Ballet in "Antique Epigraphs", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dancer Adolph Bolm of Ballets Russes, circa 1900s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Three photographs by Sasha of London of Russian dancers Alexandra Danilova and Andre Eglevsky of the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo performing "Les Sylphides", 1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dancer Arthur Mitchell (Dance Theater of Harlem) with ballerina, circa 1900s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Press photograph of composers and educators Zoltan Kodaly, Dmitry Kabalevsky, and Norman Dello Joio at Interlochen conference, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hitler Youth members playing recorders, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photograph by Martha Swope of Jerome Robbins rehearsing "Circus Polka" with young girls, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photograph by Arnold Eagle of dancer and choreographer Martha Graham in "Mirror Before Me (Heriodiade)", 1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Two photographs of Harry Partch, March 10-11, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Acquisition date - July 2012
  - Minstrel show photograph, circa 1900-1910 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Stephen Sondheim, Arthur Laurents, Harold S. Prince, Robert E. Griffith, Leonard Bernstein, and Jerome Robbins, September 29, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Acquisition date - July 2018
  - John Cage, Gordon Mumma, and David Tudor, July 5, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)